Guide to the Thelma Z. Lavine papers, 1932-2007
George Mason University. Libraries. Special Collections & Archives
Thelma Z. Lavine papers
1932-2007
C0195
George Mason University. Libraries. Special Collections & Archives
18.75 linear feet (43 boxes)
Research papers, correspondence, articles, and notes that document the career of Thelma Z. Lavine, a philosophy professor who taught at George Mason University, George Washington University, and the University of Maryland. There are also approximately 324 audiotape cassettes of lectures by Lavine as well as radio show appearances.
Lavine, Thelma Z.
Access Restrictions
There are no access restrictions.
Acquisition Information
Donated by Margaret V. Sachs in 2011.
Biographical Information
Born in Boston, Massachusetts, on February 12, 1915, Thelma Z. Lavine taught philosophy for over 40 years, mostly at universities in the Washington, D.C. area. Her teaching career began after she received doctoral degrees in Psychology and Philosophy from Harvard University in 1939. Prior to that, she completed an undergraduate degree at Radcliffe College in 1936. A popular lecturer, she taught at the University of Maryland in the 1950s and 1960s, then accepted a teaching position at George Washington University. She joined the faculty at George Mason University as a Robinson Professor in 1985 and taught there until she retired in 1998.
An active and well-respected philosophy professor, Lavine served in many organizations, including as president of the Washington Philosophy Club, on the Executive Committee of the Society for Advancement of American Philosophy, and on the Ralph Waldo Emerson Committee of the United Chapters of Phi Beta Kappa.
Lavine was trained by, knew, and debated well-known philosophers including Richard Rorty, John Dewey, C.I. Lewis, Susanne Langer, Hannah Arendt, Paul Weiss, and Kurt Wolff. After she moved to Washington, DC from Boston, one of her projects was to make American Philosophy relevant to students. In addition to advocating for the controversial American branch of philosophy, Lavine produced scholarship on social philosophy, philosophy of the social sciences, American naturalism, philosophy of history, and philosophy in literature.
A widely published author, she popularized philosophy with her 30-part series "From Socrates to Sartre: The Philosophic Quest," which aired first on Maryland Public Television and then nationally in the early 1980s. Her book of the same name was published in 1984 and is still in print. Lavine died at her home in Washington, D.C., on January 28, 2011.
Scope and Content
Research papers, correspondence, articles, and notes that document the career of Thelma Z. Lavine. There are also approximately 324 audiotape cassettes of lectures by Lavine as well as radio show appearances. The collection also includes almost 2,000 books, a small portion of which will be cataloged and housed in special collections.
Series 1, Correspondence: This series contains communications regarding Lavine's professional activities, including meetings, conferences, and symposia as well as journal submissions and presentations; correspondence relating to her MPT TV series and her book "From Socrates to Sartre: The Philosophic Quest;" correspondence with other scholars and philosophers; and fan mail from her students, readers, and viewers. This series is organized first alphabetically by subject and then chronologically.
Series 2, Research: This series contains notes, clippings, and other papers related to Lavine's work as a scholar and professional philosopher. This series includes published articles, book reviews, newspaper articles and editorials written by her and by others; research for her MPT show; and research which culminated in her book. Ranging from small local workshops to large international meetings, the conferences for which there are research, programs, and complete presentation papers cover a range of themes including the women's movement. This series also contains materials from Lavine's work as a student, scholar, and teacher. This series is first organized by subject and then chronologically.
Series 3, Publications: This series contains original books and professional journals which contain writings from Lavine. A seventh edition English-language copy of her book is present, as well as a copy of the Japanese-language edition. This series is organized chronologically.
Series 4, Audio/Visual: This series is comprised largely of audio cassette recordings. Included are classroom lectures and radio interviews, as well as a few miscellaneous items such as a memorial speech. Complete or nearly complete lecture series include "From Socrates to Sartre," "Philosophy 19th Century," "Philosophy 355," "Philosophy of America," "Philosophy of History," "Philosophy and Literature/Philosophy of Literature," and "Philosophy and Social Science/Social Philosophy." This series is organized first by subject and then chronologically.
Arrangement note
Series 1: Correspondence, 1960-2005 (Boxes 1-6)
Series 2: Research, 1930s-2007 (Boxes 6-32)
Series 3: Publications, 1977-2002 (Boxes 23-33)
Series 4: Audio/Visual, 1969-1996 (Boxes 34-43)
Related Materials
Special Collections and Archives also holds the papers of many other George Mason University professors. Lavine's work "From Socrates to Sartre" is available in book format at the Fenwick Library and in VHS format in the Johnson Center videotapes.
Index Terms
Persons:
Lavine, Thelma Z.
Subjects:
Civilization, Western--Philosophy.; Philosophy; Philosophy--History; Psychology.
Contents List
- Series 1: Correspondence, 1960-2005; (5.5 boxes)
  This series contains various types of correspondence including communications regarding Lavine's professional activities, such as meetings, conferences, and symposia, as well as journal submissions and presentations; correspondence relating to her MPT TV series and her book "From Socrates to Sartre: The Philosophic Quest;" correspondence with other scholars and philosophers; and fan mail from her students, readers, and viewers. Correspondence can also be found in the "Research" files. This series is organized first alphabetically by subject and then chronologically.
  - Accolades, 1967-1990s (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Accolades including press coverage, 1978-1990s (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - American, 1970s (Box 1, Folder 3)
    Identified by TZL. Includes SAAP material.
  - American, 1970s (Box 1, Folder 4)
    Identified by TZL. Includes research notes and clippings in addition to correspondence related to the American Philosophers Club.
  - American culture, 1986-1987 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    Seminar, courses, program.
  - American enterprise, 1979-1980 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    Fellowship, NEH
  - American philosophy, 1970-1988 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    Ayn Rand. Correspondence from GWU.
  - American philosophy, 2000s (Box 1, Folder 8)
    Founders vs. American Pragmatism; Politics; History. Items relating to GMU's Dr. Buchanan.
  - Bell, Daniel, 2001 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    Natural law, utopia.
  - Conferences, 1976-1989 (Box 2, Folder 1)
    Includes lectures and meetings.
  - Conferences, 1980s (Box 2, Folder 2)
    Includes APA material.
  - Conferences, 1982-1983 (Box 2, Folder 3)
    APA convention, philosophic societies, various.
  - Conferences, 1985-1988 (Box 2, Folder 4)
    Identified by TZL as "Current."
  - Conferences, 1981-1983 (Box 2, Folder 5)
    Includes SAAP material.
  - Cunliffe, Marcus, 1980s (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Fan mail, 1977-1982 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Fan mail, 1979-1980 (Box 2, Folder 8)
    Includes "Krebiozen," Larry King.
  - Fan mail, 1979-1982 (Box 2, Folder 9)
    Includes "hypophosphatasia."
  - Fan mail, 1979-1983 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Fan mail, 1979-1986 (Box 2, Folder 11)
    Includes "Jonathan Skipp - Bantam."
  - Fan mail, 1979-1987 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Fan mail, 1979-1990 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Fan mail, 1980-1986 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Fan mail, 1980-1989 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Goldwin, Dr. Robert A., July 23, 1980 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - "KC File", 1998-2000 (Box 3, Folder 5)
    Identified by TZL. Romantic pragmatism, American history, politics.
  - Kathy's translations, 1995 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Lewis, C.I., 1978-1980 (Box 3, Folder 7)
    The problem of phenomenalism. SUNY Buffalo.
  - Lit theory and Philosophy, 1980s (Box 3, Folder 8)
    Identified by TZL.
  - MPT and book, 1979-1980 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - MPT Series, 1980 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Meetings, 1987 (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Presentations, colleges, 1970s-1980s (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Presentations, colleges, August 16, 1975 - April 6, 1976 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Professional, 1960s (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Professional, 1970s (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Professional, 1980s (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Professional, 1981, 1992-1995 (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Professional, 1982-2002 (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Professional, 1982-2004 (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Professional, 1990-2005 (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - Psychiatry, 1990s (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - Random House, 1982 (Box 4, Folder 11)
    Identified by TZL as "Random House re SocSart"
  - Rationalization, 1990s (Box 4, Folder 12)
  - SAAP, 1984 (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - SAAP, 1990s (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Sonoma State University Lecture, 1982 (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Student mail, February 3, 1989 (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Various, 1940s-2001 (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - Various, 1961-1979 (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - Various, 1963-1989 (Box 5, Folder 7)
    Arendt, B'nai B'rith, The New Yorker.
  - Various, 1964-1990 (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - Various, 1965-1990 (Box 5, Folder 9)
  - Various, 1965-1990 (Box 6, Folder 1)
    Nazism, fan mail, Pragmatism, Arendt.
  - Various, 1966-2000 (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - Various, 1979-2001 (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - Various, 1987-2003 (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - Various, 1991-1992 (Box 6, Folder 5)
  - Virginia Center for the Humanities, 1989 (Box 6, Folder 6)
  - Virginia Foundation for the Humanities Colloquium, 1989 (Box 6, Folder 7)
  - White House, 1991 (Box 6, Folder 8)
- Series 2: Research, 1930s-2007; (24.5 boxes)
  This series contains notes, clippings, and other papers related to Lavine's work as a scholar and professional philosopher. This series includes published articles, book reviews, newspaper articles and editorials written by her and by others; research which culminated in her MPT show and her book. Ranging from small local workshops to large international meetings, the conferences for which there are research, programs, and complete presentation papers cover a range of themes including the women's movement. This series also contains materials from Lavine's work as a student, scholar, and teacher. This series is first organized alphabetically by subject and then chronologically.
  - 19th Century papers, 1960s-1970 (Box 6, Folder 9)
  - 19th Century papers, 1983-1993 (Box 6, Folder 10)
    includes paper by Alan Wood at Cornell.
  - 19th Century papers, undated (Box 6, Folder 11)
  - A-C binder contents, 1990s (Box 7, Folder 1)
    Original binder tabs identified contents as "America, American Phil., American Creed, Capitalism, Chaos, Communism, Communitarianism, Contemp., Counterculture, Counter Enlight."
  - A-D binder contents, 1990s (Box 7, Folder 2)
    Original binder tabs identified contents as "Arendt, Bell, Bellah, Bernstein, C, Blake, Bloom, Diggins."
  - Academic papers, 1930s (Box 7, Folder 3)
  - Academic papers, 1930s (Box 7, Folder 4)
    Includes high school yearbooks with photos.
  - Academic papers, 1930s (Box 7, Folder 5)
  - Academic papers, 1930s (Box 7, Folder 6)
  - Academic papers, 1930s (Box 7, Folder 7)
  - Academic papers, 1930s (Box 8, Folder 1)
  - Academic papers, 1930s (Box 8, Folder 2)
  - Academic papers, 1930s (Box 8, Folder 3)
  - Academic papers, 1930s (Box 8, Folder 4)
    Includes work on history and religion.
  - Academic papers, 1930s (Box 8, Folder 5)
    Kant.
  - Academic papers, 1930s (Box 8, Folder 6)
    Logical positivism.
  - Academic papers, 1930s (Box 8, Folder 7)
    Santayana.
  - Academic papers, 1930s (Box 8, Folder 8)
    "Speech in Society."
  - Academic papers, 1930s (Box 8, Folder 9)
    Undergraduate. Radcliffe.
  - Academic papers, 1930s (Box 8, Folder 10)
    Undergraduate honors thesis on knowledge and other minds.
  - Alumnae Recognition Award and related documents, 1989-1991 (Box 8, Folder 11)
  - American Council on Education, Women in Education, 1972 (Box 8, Folder 12)
  - America - historical, classical, and current, 1980s-1990s (Box 8, Folder 13)
  - American culture, 1979-1980 (Box 9, Folder 1)
    Morality, capitalism, values.
  - American culture, 1980s (Box 9, Folder 2)
  - American culture, 1980s (Box 9, Folder 3)
    Identified by TZL as "Am & Crisis & Modernity."
  - American culture, undated (Box 9, Folder 4)
    Liberty. Isaiah Berlin.
  - American Exceptionalism, 1990s (Box 9, Folder 5)
  - American Philosophic Tradition, 1990s (Box 10, Folder 1)
  - American Philosophy, 1964-1981 (Box 10, Folder 2)
  - American Philosophy, 1970s-1990s (Box 10, Folder 3)
  - American Philosophy, modernity, 1980s-1991 (Box 10, Folder 4)
  - American Politics, entitlement, liberalism, Sandel, 1996 (Box 10, Folder 5)
  - American, various publications, 1974-1994 (Box 10, Folder 6)
  - Annual reports and awards, 1980-1982 (Box 10, Folder 7)
  - APA, 1983-1993 (Box 10, Folder 8)
    Committee on pluralism, executive committee, nominations.
  - Aristotle rhetoric, undated (Box 10, Folder 9)
  - Arendt and Jewishness, 1963-1982 (Box 10, Folder 10)
  - Aucott, McGarry, January 5, 1999 (Box 10, Folder 11)
  - Augustine, natural law, Latin, undated (Box 10, Folder 12)
  - Awards from CV file, 1990s (Box 10, Folder 13)
  - Baeck, Battis, Antinum, Roman religion, undated (Box 10, Folder 14)
  - Bakunin and Tolstoy, undated (Box 11, Folder 1)
  - Bell, Daniel, 1990, 1992 (Box 11, Folder 2)
    "Cultural Wars." "Resolving the Contradiction."
  - Berlin, Isaiah, 1997-1999 (Box 11, Folder 3)
  - Berman, Lears, modernity, and capitalism, 1979-1982 (Box 11, Folder 4)
  - Bibliography from Brooklyn College, 1948-1979 (Box 11, Folder 5)
  - Biomedical Ethics Conference, 1977, 1979 (Box 11, Folder 6)
  - Bishop Hurst lecture, 1991-1992 (Box 11, Folder 7)
  - Bloom, relativism, dualism, 1990s (Box 11, Folder 8)
  - Book - "Illustrations", 1933-1984 (Box 11, Folder 9)
    Identified by TZL. Identified by TZL.
  - Book - "Intro - II", 1940s-1950s (Box 11, Folder 10)
  - Book - proposal, 1949-1960s (Box 11, Folder 11)
  - British Empiricism, undated (Box 11, Folder 12)
    Berlin, psychological method.
  - Broad, C.D., 1930s-1940s (Box 11, Folder 13)
  - CV papers and supporting documentation, 1987-1990 (Box 11, Folder 14)
  - CVs and supporting documentation, 1990s (Box 11, Folder 15)
  - Camus, Albert, 1950s-1970s (Box 11, Folder 16)
  - Classical American Philosophy, 1980s (Box 11, Folder 17)
  - Classical American philosophers, 1990s (Box 11, Folder 18)
    Dewey, Feuer, NYT book reviews.
  - Collingwood, R. G., undated (Box 11, Folder 19)
  - Collingwood, R. G., undated (Box 11, Folder 20)
  - Comte, Auguste, undated (Box 12, Folder 1)
  - Conducet - 18th century, 1950s-1982 (Box 12, Folder 2)
  - Constitution project, 1979-1982 (Box 12, Folder 3)
  - Constitution project and Dewey, 1981 (Box 12, Folder 4)
  - Contemporary issues, 1996 (Box 12, Folder 5)
  - Contemporary significance of the American tradition, 1990s (Box 12, Folder 6)
  - "DSW" papers, 1978, 1979 (Box 12, Folder 7)
  - Derrida and deconstruction, 1980s (Box 12, Folder 8)
  - Derrida and Postmodernism/Foucault, 1987-1993 (Box 12, Folder 9)
  - Descartes - Scripts, 1940s-1950s (Box 12, Folder 10)
  - Dewey, John, 1970s (Box 12, Folder 11)
  - Dewey, John, 1979 (Box 12, Folder 12)
  - Dewey, John, 1980s-1990s (Box 12, Folder 13)
  - Dewey, John, 1980s-1990s (Box 12, Folder 14)
  - Dewey, John, undated (Box 12, Folder 15)
  - Dewey/Marx, and ideology, undated (Box 12, Folder 16)
  - Dewey/Sartre - "What have we learned?", 1992 (Box 12, Folder 17)
  - Dictionary of American Philosophers, 2001 (Box 13, Folder 1)
  - Diggins and pragmatism, 1990s (Box 13, Folder 2)
  - Dilthey, Wilhelm, 1982 (Box 13, Folder 3)
  - Dilthey/Husserl and intentionality, 1980s (Box 13, Folder 4)
  - Durkheim and Freud, 1930s-1950s (Box 13, Folder 5)
  - Eliade, Mircea, 1940s-1970s (Box 13, Folder 6)
  - Eliade, Mircea, 1980s (Box 13, Folder 7)
  - Eliade, Mircea, 1980s (Box 13, Folder 8)
    Includes obituary.
  - Eliade, Mircea, 1980s-1990s (Box 13, Folder 9)
  - Eliade, Mircea, 1980s-1990s (Box 13, Folder 10)
  - Emotions and humor, 1940s-1950s (Box 13, Folder 11)
    Includes realia.
  - Enlightenment, Romanticism, Reformation, and Counter, 1982-1993 (Box 13, Folder 12)
  - Epilogue, undated (Box 13, Folder 13)
  - Ernst & Ernst 1968, 1978-1980 (Box 13, Folder 14)
  - F-J binder contents, 1 of 2, 1990s (Box 13, Folder 15)
    Original binder tabs identified contents as "Emerson, Freud, Fukuyama, Gellner, Hegel, Heidegger, Hook, Hopper, Huntington, James, Jefferson / see also Amer. Creed."
  - F-J binder contents, 2 of 2, 1990s (Box 14, Folder 1)
  - Fichte, Johann Gottlieb, 1960s - 1970s (Box 14, Folder 2)
  - Folders, undated (Box 14, Folder 3)
    Copies of manila file folders on which TZL had written.
  - Foucault, Michel, 1980s (Box 14, Folder 4)
  - Foucault, Michel, 1980-2000s (Box 14, Folder 5)
  - Framework, CLOP, modernity, 1990s (Box 14, Folder 6)
  - Gadamer - hermeneutics and Ricoeur, 1985-1986 (Box 14, Folder 7)
  - Glendon, 1999-2000s (Box 14, Folder 8)
  - Globalization, 2002-2003 (Box 14, Folder 9)
  - Godwin, William, 1980s (Box 14, Folder 10)
  - Gray/Bernstein/Weinreb papers, 1960s-1990s (Box 14, Folder 11)
  - Gray, John N., 1990s (Box 14, Folder 12)
  - Gray vs. Enlightenment vs. Fukuyama, 1992-2006 (Box 14, Folder 13)
  - Greek papers and Phil 180, undated (Box 14, Folder 14)
  - GWU and NHI conference, 1976 (Box 14, Folder 15)
  - Habermas, Jürgen, 1980-1996 (Box 14, Folder 16)
    Identified by TZL as "Hab, Rorty, Bell, L. Goldstein, Modernity."
  - Habermas, Jürgen, 1982-1997 (Box 14, Folder 17)
  - Habermas - modernity, 1980s (Box 14, Folder 18)
  - Habermas - "Philosophy and the Dialectic of Modernity", 1993-2000 (Box 15, Folder 1)
  - Habermas, Jürgen, undated (Box 15, Folder 2)
  - Habermas, Jürgen, undated (Box 15, Folder 3)
  - Habits of the Heart, undated (Box 15, Folder 4)
  - Harvard, Judaism, 1960s-2004 (Box 15, Folder 5)
  - Harvard, 1986, 2001 (Box 15, Folder 6)
  - Harvard magazine, 1982-1984 (Box 15, Folder 7)
  - Harvard News, 1986 (Box 15, Folder 8)
  - Health - mind/body/soul, 1980s (Box 15, Folder 9)
  - Hegel, Georg Wilhelm Friedrich, 1960s-1970s (Box 15, Folder 10)
  - Hegel, Dewey, Sartre, 1950-1980s (Box 15, Folder 11)
  - Hegel, Heidegger, World Spirit, real/rational, 1950s-1990s (Box 15, Folder 12)
  - Hegel, Georg Wilhelm Friedrich, undated (Box 16, Folder 1)
  - Hegelian theory, undated (Box 16, Folder 2)
  - Heidegger, Martin, 1980s (Box 16, Folder 3)
  - Heidegger and Nazism, 1980s (Box 16, Folder 4)
  - Heidegger, Paul Deman, and related, 1989-1990 (Box 16, Folder 5)
  - Heidegger and Nazism, 1989-1990 (Box 16, Folder 6)
  - Hermeneutics and phenomenology, 1980s (Box 16, Folder 7)
  - Historicism, 1950s-1960s (Box 16, Folder 8)
  - History and American issues, 1960s-1980s (Box 16, Folder 9)
    Also contains TZL's resignation letter from UMD.
  - History and knowledge, June 1950 (Box 16, Folder 10)
  - History, spirituality, "Chapter 19", 1970s-1980s (Box 16, Folder 11)
  - History of Philosophy, 1940s-1950s (Box 16, Folder 12)
  - History of Philosophy, 1940s-1980s (Box 16, Folder 13)
  - History of Philosophy, 1950s-1960s (Box 16, Folder 14)
  - History of Philosophy, 1 of 2, October 19, 1980 - April 20, 2000 (Box 16, Folder 15)
  - History of Philosophy, 2 of 2, October 19, 1980 - April 20, 2000 (Box 17, Folder 1)
  - History of Philosophy, 1953-2001 (Box 17, Folder 2)
  - Hofstra conference, Americanism, 1942-1981 (Box 17, Folder 3)
  - Horowitz, modernity, human rights, self, 2000s (Box 17, Folder 4)
  - Horowitz, various, 2005 (Box 17, Folder 5)
  - Howard University, 1992 (Box 17, Folder 6)
  - Hume, David, undated (Box 17, Folder 7)
    Identified by TZL as "tv program script and notes"
  - Husserl, hermeneutics, 1980s (Box 17, Folder 8)
  - Ideal type and interpretivism, undated (Box 17, Folder 9)
  - Ideology and utopia, 1936-1940s (Box 17, Folder 10)
  - interpretivism, American, modernity, 1979-1985 (Box 17, Folder 11)
  - "Intro", 1960s-1970s (Box 17, Folder 12)
  - Jewish and anti-Semite issues and related lecture, 1960s-1990s (Box 17, Folder 13)
  - Jews and Nazism, 1960s (Box 17, Folder 14)
  - Jews, concentration camps, Arendt, 1960s-1980s (Box 17, Folder 15)
  - "Jordy" note, undated (Box 18, Folder 1)
  - Judaism in the Culture of Modernism, 1980s (Box 18, Folder 2)
  - K-R binder contents, 1990s (Box 18, Folder 3)
    Original binder tabs identified contents as "Kant, Kloppenberg, Lasch, Lincoln, Lipset, Malia, Mann, Pierce [sic], Rawls."
  - Kant, Immanuel, 1940s-1950s (Box 18, Folder 4)
  - Kant, Immanuel, 1957-1960 (Box 18, Folder 5)
  - Kant, Immanuel, 2001 (Box 18, Folder 6)
  - Kant, Immanuel, undated (Box 18, Folder 7)
  - Kierkegaard, Søren, 1966-1980s (Box 18, Folder 8)
  - "Knowledge as Interpretation", 1983-1985 (Box 18, Folder 9)
  - Krikorian memorial service, 1977-1978 (Box 18, Folder 10)
  - Leave request and supporting documentation, 1980s-1990s (Box 18, Folder 11)
  - Lectures and lecture notes, 1981-1988 (Box 18, Folder 12)
  - "Lee lectures on", 1930s-1950s (Box 18, Folder 13)
  - Lewis, phenomenalism, SAAP, 1970s-1980s (Box 19, Folder 1)
  - Library seminar, American culture, March 3, 1987 (Box 19, Folder 2)
  - Liberalism/conservatism, American culture, 1970s (Box 19, Folder 3)
  - Liberalism, science, ideology, 1990s (Box 19, Folder 4)
  - Library related items including news and book lists, 1970s (Box 19, Folder 5)
  - Lipset and American politics, 1990s (Box 19, Folder 6)
  - Lipset library fund, 2000s (Box 19, Folder 7)
  - Lipset medical issues, 2001-2002 (Box 19, Folder 8)
  - Literature, 1997-2000 (Box 19, Folder 9)
  - Literature and art, 1990s (Box 19, Folder 10)
  - M-S binder contents, 1990s (Box 19, Folder 11)
    Original binder tabs identified contents as "Modernity, Millenium, Multiculturalism, Overview, Pluralism, Politics, Postmodernism, Pragmatism, Religion, Socialism."
  - Mannheim, 1981-1982 (Box 19, Folder 12)
  - "Marcell, progress & pragmatism; Kaplan", undated (Box 19, Folder 13)
  - "Meaning of Meaning", 1930s (Box 20, Folder 1)
  - Modernism, 1960s-1970s (Box 20, Folder 2)
  - Modernism, 1975-1983 (Box 20, Folder 3)
  - Modernism, 1980s (Box 20, Folder 4)
  - Modernism, philosophy, and literature, 1988 (Box 20, Folder 5)
  - Modernity, 1962-1991 (Box 20, Folder 6)
  - Modernity, 1967-1980 (Box 20, Folder 7)
  - Modernity, 1980s-1990s (Box 20, Folder 8)
  - Modernity, 1988-1995 (Box 21, Folder 1)
  - Modernity, 1989 (Box 21, Folder 2)
  - Modernity, 1990s (Box 21, Folder 3)
    Includes history and "Kant's Children."
  - Modernity and naturalism, 1991 (Box 21, Folder 4)
  - NEH grant application and supporting documents, 1970s (Box 21, Folder 5)
  - NEH grant and fellowship application, 1970s-1990s (Box 21, Folder 6)
  - NEH papers, 1980s (Box 21, Folder 7)
  - Nietzsche, undated (Box 21, Folder 8)
  - Nietzsche, undated (Box 21, Folder 9)
  - Nietzsche, undated (Box 21, Folder 10)
  - "Nozick, Galileo, etc.", 1982, 1988 (Box 21, Folder 11)
  - Obituaries, 2000-2003 (Box 21, Folder 12)
    Goode, Quine, Feuer, Merton, Weiss, Anger, Phillips.
  - Parsons/American, 1985 (Box 22, Folder 1)
  - Philosophy as a Vocation, 1960s (Box 22, Folder 2)
  - Philosophy and history, 1960s (Box 22, Folder 3)
  - Philosophy of history, 1940s-1960s (Box 22, Folder 4)
  - Pluralism, APA, 1990s (Box 22, Folder 5)
  - Political events, 1982-1996 (Box 22, Folder 6)
  - Politics and NPR, 1980s (Box 22, Folder 7)